Guide to the Henry Guerlac papers, 1922-1981
Guerlac, Henry papers, 1922-1981
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry Guerlac papers, 1922-1981
14-17-2354
Henry Guerlac.
34.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence; notebooks; photographs and negatives; photograph albums; scrapbooks; drawings; radio transcripts; journals; thesis and dissertation; drafts and galley proofs; articles; reports; book reviews; lecture notes and syllabi; research materials, including notes, bibliographies, and photocopies of manuscripts; and miscellaneous papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes papers pertaining to Guerlac's research and teaching career.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry Edward Guerlac (1910-1982) graduated from Cornell University in 1932, received a master's degree in biochemistry from Cornell in 1933, and a doctorate in European history from Harvard University in 1941. Before joining the Cornell faculty in 1946, he taught at Harvard and the University of Wisconsin, and for three years was the historian for the Radiation Laboratory of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In 1964, he was named Goldwin Smith Professor of the History of Science and in 1970 he became director of the Society for the Humanities at Cornell. Guerlac was awarded the George Sarton Medal by the History of Science Society in 1973, was named a Guggenheim Fellow in 1978, and in 1982 was named Chevalier de la Légion d'Honneur by the French government.
Guerlac's books include Science in Western Civilization, Newton on the Continent, and Lavoisier: The Crucial Year, for which he received the Pfizer Prize in 1959. At the time of his death Professor Guerlac was completing an annotated edition of Newton's Opticks, which was first published in 1704.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The majority of the papers in this collection pertain to Guerlac's teaching career and to the writing and publication of his book on Isaac Newton. Included are correspondence; notebooks; photographs and negatives; photograph albums; scrapbooks; drawings; radio transcripts; journals; his thesis and dissertation; drafts and galley proofs, articles, reports, book reviews, and other materials pertaining to Guerlac's published works; lecture notes and syllabi for courses Guerlac taught at Cornell; research materials, including notes, bibliographies, and photocopies of manuscripts; and miscellaneous papers relating to Guerlac's personal and professional activities. Subjects include Guerlac's work at Harvard, Yale, MIT, Wisconsin, and Cornell; students; the history of science and the history of ideas; a variety of scientific topics, including astronomy (comets), biology, botany, chemistry, geology, radar, optics and color; math; publications, including History of Science, Journal of the History of Ideas, Isis, and others; editing and publishing; the Sarton Award; the History of Science Society; 17th and 18th century figures, including Newton (and the Opticks), Boscovich, Lavoisier, La Brosse (Ange de Saint-Joseph), and Galileo; and personal papers concerning music (especially violin), his boyhood and education, Vicious Circle Club, the Ithaca Festival, travel, and other topics.
The collection also includes research files, drafts, and correspondence relating to an edition of Newton's Opticks, never published; reprints of Guerlac's articles; and subject files of notes and research materials relating to eighteenth century history, particularly the French Revolution, and to eighteenth century science, particularly chemistry and biology.
Correspondents include Marie Boas (Hall), Denis I. Duveen, Roger Hahn, Rio Howard, Robert Kargon, David Kubrin, William Langer, Harry Woolf, L. Pearce Williams, Betty Jo Dobbs, Margaret Candee Jacob, George Sarton, Bernard Cohen, W.J. King, James B. Sumner, and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Guerlac, Henry.; Ange de Saint-Joseph, 1636-1697.; Boscovich, Ruggero Giuseppe, 1711-1787.; Cohen, I. Bernard, 1914-; Dobbs, Betty Jo Teeter, 1930-; Duveen, Denis I.; Galilei, Galileo, 1564-1642.; Hahn, Roger, 1932-; Hall, Marie Boas, 1919-; Howard, Rio.; Kargon, Robert.; King, W. J. (William Joseph), b. 1881.; Kubrin, David.; Langer, William L. (William Leonard), 1896-1977.; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794.; Newton, Isaac, Sir, 1642-1727. Opticks.; Sarton, George, 1884-1956.; Sumner, James B. (James Batcheller), 1887-1955.; Williams, L. Pearce (Leslie Pearce), 1927-; Woolf, Harry.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Harvard University--Faculty.; Massachusetts Institute of Technology--Faculty.; Yale University--Faculty.; History of Science Society.; Ithaca Festival (Ithaca, N.Y.); Vicious Circle Club (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Astronomy.; Biology.; Botany.; Chemistry.; Color--Study and teaching.; Comets.; Geology.; Mathematics.; Music.; Radar.; Science--History--Study and teaching.; College teachers.; Historians of science.
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Manuscripts.; Negatives.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal
Boxes 1-2
1. Boyhood and youth, early correspondence, music
Box 1
2. Photographs
Box 2
Series II. Harvard and Yale
Box 3
Series III. Wisconsin, MIT (Radiation Lab), Cornell
Box 4
Series IV. Guerlac at Cornell, 1946-1977
Box 5
Series V. Guerlac syllabus, readings, University Microfilms
Box 6
Series VI. History of Science Society
Boxes 6-7
Series VII. History of science material
Boxes 7-8
Series VIII. Early drafts and articles
Boxes 8-9
Series IX. Comets
Box 9
Series X. Books, papers, drafts
Boxes 9-10
Series XI. Lectures, papers, reviews
Boxes 10-11
Series XII. Correspondence file: Cornell students and colleagues, A-Z
Boxes 11-12
Series XIII. Journal of the History of Ideas
Box 12
Series XIV. Student offprints
Box 12
Series XV. Correspondence, 1965-1984
Boxes 12-13
Series XVI. Correspondence, A-Z
Box 13
Series XVII. Lecture notes: Survey course in the history of science
Boxes 13-14
Series XVIII. 17th- and 18th-century material for articles in progress
Boxes 14-15
Series XIX. Newton files
Boxes 16-17
1. Bibliography
Box 17
2. Analysis
Box 17
3. Atomism
Box 17
4. Cartesianism
Box 17
5. Newton on chemistry
Box 17
6. Chronology
Box 17
7. Newton on experiment
Box 17
8. Gravity
Box 17
9. Newton on hypotheses
Box 17
10. Theory of matter
Box 17
11. Newton on mechanics
Box 17
12. The Opticks
Box 17
13. Qualities, intensions, and remission
Box 17
14. Newton on religion
Box 17
15. 17th-century figures
Box 17
Series XX. Newton: Chemistry, Opticks
Box 18
1. History of color
Box 18
2. Correspondence: Opticks projects, etc.
Box 18
3. Editorial procedures
Box 18
Series XXI. Editing and publishing
Box 18
1. Printing of Opticks
Box 18
2. Material for introduction
Box 18
3. Newton manuscript
Box 18
4. Modern translations
Box 18
Series XXII. Newton and Boscovitch
Box 18
Series XXIII. Newton: Color and light
Box 19
Series XXIV. 17th-century figures
Box 19
Series XXV. Newton's Opticks: Drafts, photocopies of Newton's editions, notes
Box 20
Series XXVI. Newton's Opticks: Notes, preliminary working copies, photocopies and galley proofs
Box 21
Series XXVII. Lavoisier: Photocopies and drafts
Box 22
Series XXVIII. Typescript lectures and photocopied articles
Box 23
Series XXIX. History of Science Society, Isis matters, Sarton Medal awards
Box 24
Series XXX. Bowman committee, 1944-1945
Box 25
Series XXXI. Personal correspondence: Alphabetical, 1939-1975
Box 25
Series XXXII. Chronological correspondence, 1940-1975
Boxes 26-27
Series XXXIII. Correspondence, 1946-1956
Boxes 29-30
Series XXXIV. Correspondence, 1957-1963
Box 30
Series XXXV. Guerlac and Cornell
Boxes 30-34
Series XXXVI. Other
Box 40
Series XXXVII. Unprocessed material: Opticks, subject files, reprints, "The First Book"
Boxes 35-39
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal
  - Boyhood and youth, early correspondence, music
    - Nature Study Notebook (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Trees (Ferns), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Trees, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Souvenir de ma traversée sur S.S. "Roussillon,", 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Field Report on Local Birds, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Herbarium, 1925, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Boy Scout Troop 4; Bird Chart, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence; Bird Charts, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Miscellany, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Physical Laboratory, c., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Thesis: The Thiocyanate Anion and Cytoplasmic Viscosity, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellany, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Quartets (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Music (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Accident - Chicago, Feb. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Other Personal Letters, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Violin (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs, photo albums, scrapbooks, sketches, medals
    - Photograph Albums, 1923-1928 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1923-1925 (Box 2)
    - Chemistry Workbook, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Theory and Literature Discussion, Sketch Book I, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Experimental Data, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Drawings - Embryological, Entomological (Box 2)
    - The Journal of the American Medical Association, July 2, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Boy Scout Medals (Box 2)
- Series II: Harvard and Yale
  - Revue du Genie Militaire, May-June 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Revue du Genie Militaire, July-Aug. 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ecole de Mezieres (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Science and War in the Old Regime --A Dissertation, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4-9)
  - Student Paper: "The British in Egypt" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Harvard (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - WRUL - "Radio Boston," France (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Yale (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Early Development of Science: An Essay," Part I, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Early Development of Science: An Essay," Part II, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chinese Science (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - History 311: Lecture 23, The Renaissance (also Explorations and Cartography) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - History 311: The Copernican Revolution (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - History 311: Lecture 30, William. Gilbert (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - History 311: Lecture 26, Renaissance Natural History (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - History 311: Lecture 27, Mathematics in the 16th and 17th Centuries (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - History 311: Tycho and Kepler (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - History 311: Lecture 29, Galileo I (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - History 311: Lecture 31, Galileo III (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - History 311: Lecture 32, The Paduan Anatomists and Harvey (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - History 311: Notes for Review Lecture (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - History 312: Paris, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - History 312: Lecture 1 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - History 312: Lecture 2 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - History 312: Lecture 3 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - History 312: Lecture 4 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - History 312: Lecture 5, Eighteenth Century Math (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - History 312: Lecture 6 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - History 312: Lecture 7 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - History 312: Mechanics (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - History 312: Lecture 8 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - History 312: Lecture 9 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - History 312: Lecture 10 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - History 312: Lecture 11, Biological Theory (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - History 312: Lecture 12 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - History 312: Lecture 13 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - History 312: Lecture 14 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - History 312: Lecture 15, Observation Astronomy (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - History 312: Lecture 16 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - History 312: The Development of Early Chemistry (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - History 312: Lecture 17 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - History 312: Lecture 18 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - History 312: Lecture 19 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - History 312: Lecture 20 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - History 312: Lecture 21 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - History 312: Lecture 22 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - History 312: Lecture 23, Boscovitch to Dalton (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - History 312: Lecture 24, Geology (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - History 312: Lecture 25, Biological Evolution--Lamarck to Darwin (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - History 312: Lecture 26 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - History 312: Lecture 27, Physiology in the 19th Century, Bichat to Bernard (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - History 312: Lecture 28, Cell Theory (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - History 312: Lecture 29, Light (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - History 312: Lecture 30, Volta, Oersted, etc. (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - History 312: Lecture 31, Faraday and Maxwell (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - History 312: Lecture 32, Conservation of Energy (I) (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - History 312: Lecture 33, Heat and Thermodynamics (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - History 312: Medicine in 19th Century (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - History 312: Lecture 34, Impact of Science (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - History 312: Lecture 35, Karl Marx (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - History 312: Lecture 35a, Astronomy in the 19th Century (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - History 312: Lecture 36, Molecules and Divisible Atoms (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - History 312: Biology and Genetics after Darwin (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - History 312: Watson - DNA (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - History 312: Lecture 37, Radioactivity and Atomic Energy (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - American Science; American Philanthropy for Science (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - American Science: Lectures 1-10 (#8 is missing) (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - American Science: Lectures 11-15 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - American Science: Lectures 16-22 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - American Science: Lectures 23-26 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - American Science: Lecture 27 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Notes on History of American Science (Box 3, Folder 77)
- Series III: Wisconsin, MIT (Radiation Lab), Cornell
  - Confidential (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wisconsin Appointment (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Wisconsin - Science Courses (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Wisconsin - History I (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hogben - History of Science at Wisconsin (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wisconsin - History of Science Seminar (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - France Forever (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - France Forever - Wisconsin, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "The Problem of France" - Radio address at Wisconsin, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Wisconsin--Trends in Contemporary Civilization (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - University of Wisconsin, History of Science I (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Minnesota - Summer, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - University of Wisconsin, Massachussetts Institute of Technology--Personal (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - World War II (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Radiation Lab (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - History of Science, Massachussetts Institute of Technology, Personal (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Wisconsin State Retirement (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - I.B. Cohen, 1943-1947 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    See also box 5 folders 2-4.
  - American Federation of Scientists (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - The Tannery Club (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Ohio State: Harold Grimm, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - History of Science at Cornell, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Book Review: Scientific American Reader (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Book Review: Lynde Phelps Wheeler: Josiah Willard Gibbs: The History of a Great Mind, review in Science, July, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Review: I. Bernard Cohen: Some Early Tools of American Science (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Review: Von Laue: History of Physics, Coulson: Joseph Henry (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Book Review: Sir Charles Sherrington, OM: The Endeavor of Jean Fernel, with a list of Editions, etc., Mar. 1950 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Review: Goudsmit's Alsos (Isis), May 1949 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Review: Giedion's Mechanization Takes Command, (American Quarterly), Apr. 1949 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Review: Fraser's Half-Hours with Great Scientists, (Physics Today), Nov. 1948 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Review: Fulton and Thomson's Benjamin Silliman, ( New England Quarterly), Oct. 1948 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Review: Pledge's Science Since 1500 ( William and Mary Quarterly), Oct. 1947 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Review: O'Neil's Tesla, Autumn, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Review: Cohen's Benjamin Franklin's Experiments, (New England Quarterly), Jan. 1942 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Review: Rukeyser's Willard Gibbs, (Survey of Current Literature), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Book Review: A.R. Hall, Ballistics in the 17th Century, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Radar Paper, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Cornell Review, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Fulbright Committee, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - James M. Osborn (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - American Philanthropy: E. Emerson Andrews, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - National Science Foundation Meeting (NSF) (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science: Section L, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - I. Bernard Cohen: "Some Recent Books on the History of Science," Journal of the History of Ideas, XV,, pp. 177-8, Jan. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - American Council of Learned Societies Committee (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Lectureships (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Lectures by Prof. Shiras (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - The International Congress for the History of Science, Jerusalem, Aug. 1953 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Commission on the Teaching of the History of Science (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Radio and Television Committee (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1953 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 54-55)
  - The Institute for Advanced Study (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, Institute for Advanced Study (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Records of Trip to England, Scotland, France, and Switzerland, Apr.-Sept. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Assignment Sheets - 1952, 2nd folder (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Attacks on Science (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - I.B. Cohen - "Newton's Mathematical Way" (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Toronto Session, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Rochester Visit--Ted Brown, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, 1982, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - School of Historical Studies, Visiting Committee, Dec. 17-18, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 65-68)
  - Institute for Advanced Studies, Visiting Committee (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Series IV: Guerlac at Cornell, 1946-1977
  - "The Historians' Treatment of Science: Survey of Typical Contemporary Textbooks of History" - Report to Dean Richtmyer (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - History of Science - Personal (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Rockefeller Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Books Recently Purchased, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rockefeller Grant, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kudos (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Morris Bishop (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ithaca Chamber Orchestra (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Science and Research at Cornell, 1948-1953 (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
  - Vicious Circle (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Save Cayuga Lake (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Stevenson Statement (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Proposal for Performing Art (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - A.D. White Professors-at-Large (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Social Science Research Committee--Cornell, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Celebration Committee - Cornell, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Policy Committee - Cornell, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Reports--Undergraduate Education, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Reports--Morison Report, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Reports--Guerlac Report, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Reports--Humanities Council Report, Oct. 1969 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Reports--Doctorates (Cornell), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Reports--Graduate School, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - University Microfilms, Inc. (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Report on History of Science at Cornell, 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - University Library (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Cornell University Library and History of Science (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Xth International Congress, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 33-34)
  - D. Schullian and List of Science Collections (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Academie des Sciences--Lavoisier Committee (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
  - Lavoisier Collection (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Neale Watson and Bob Multhauf (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Lavoisier Collection - Cornell (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Library (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Library and Lavoisier Collection, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Lafayette Papers (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Berzelius Collection (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Book Sellers and Buying (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Book Sellers - England and Continent (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Book Sellers - U.S. (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Guggenheim (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - Material on the Humanities (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Sarton Medal (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Personal, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Society for the Humanities (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Howard Mumford Jones (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - A.D. White House (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Society for the Humanities (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
  - The Sacking of Henry Guerlac (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Freshman Humanities (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Science and Literature (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Autobiography (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Personal (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Phylloxera (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Humanities miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 64)
- Series V: Guerlac syllabus, readings, University Microfilms
  - Copyright of Syllabus (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Source Material (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Syllabus History 166 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Selected Readings in The History of Science, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Selected Readings in The History of Science, Volume II, Part I, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Selected Readings in The History of Science, Volume II, Part II, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with publishers re reprint rights for Volume I (Box 6, Folder 7-12)
  - Reader Vol. I, Material not used (Box 6, Folder 13-15)
  - Selected Readings in the History of Science (acknowledgments) (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Appendix: Additional material that may be of use (Box 6, Folder 17-19)
  - Reader--Suggestions for new edition (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Bibliography and suggestions for reader (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence in selling the reader (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Copyright certificate of registration (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Acknowledgment of syllabus and reader (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Astronomy paper (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Catalogue of the William Barclay Parsons Collection (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - University Microfilms--Materials (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - University Microfilms--Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 28-29)
  - Microfilm bought under its grant and given to the University Library (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - History of Science: I. Reference Collection, Copy 9 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - History of Science: II. Topical Collection, Copy 9 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (30-33a), Copy 9 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (33b-34b), Copy 9 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (34c-35c), Copy 9 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - History of Science: I. Reference Collection, Copy 6 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - History of Science: II. Topical Collection, Copy 6 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (30-33a), Copy 6 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (33b-34b), Copy 6 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - History of Science: III. Chronological Collection (34c-35c) (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Chronological Collection (Box 6, Folder 41-44)
- Series VI: History of Science Society
  - "History of Science and the Study of Society" (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - The writing of research papers (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - History of history of science (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Younger prospects in the history of science (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Foreign museums and libraries (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Journals of the history of science (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Museums of science and technology (Box 7, Folder 2)